<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine deuout and godly petitions, commonly called, Iesus Psalter</title>
            <title>Jesus psalter.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1575</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 42 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04437</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14563.3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107390</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843091</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843091</idno>
            <idno type="VID">7800</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04437)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 7800)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 441:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine deuout and godly petitions, commonly called, Iesus Psalter</title>
                  <title>Jesus psalter.</title>
                  <author>Whitford, Richard, fl. 1495-1555?, attributed name. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64+] p. : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Apud Iohan. Foulerum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Antwerpiæ :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Anno. 1575.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Sometimes attributed to Richard Whitford.</note>
                  <note>With woodcut on verso of first title page--STC.</note>
                  <note>In two parts. Part 2, "Godly contemplations for the vnlearned", is a series of 61 woodcuts.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D +.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 14565.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 14565 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect; lacks part 2.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic Church --  Prayer-books and devotions --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:1"/>
            <p>Certaine deuout and Godly Petitions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called, IESVS PSALTER.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>Non eſt aliud Nomen datum hominibus. <bibl>Act. 4.</bibl>
               </q>
               <p>IHS</p>
            </figure>
            <q>There is none other name vnder heauen giuen vnto men, in which we muſt be ſaued. <bibl>Act. 4.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>ANTVERPIAE. <hi>Apud Iohan. Foulerum. Anno.</hi> 1575.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:2"/>
            <q>Miſerere meî, Ieſu, fili Dauid.</q>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <head>The Woman of Chanane ceaſſed not to crie. <bibl>Matth. 15.</bibl>
                  </head>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <q>
               <p>Haue mercie on me, Ieſu, the Sonne of Dauid.</p>
               <p>O Lord, helpe me.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="Psalter">
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:2"/>
            <head>Certaine deuout and Godly Petitions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called. Ieſus Pſalter.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, that ther be three maner of Pſalters.</p>
            <p>The Fyrſte is called Dauids Pſalter, which conteineth thries Fifty Pſalmes. The ſeconde is called the Pſalter of our Ladie, conteining thryes Fyfty Aues. The thyrd is called
<pb facs="tcp:7800:3"/>the Pſalter of Ieſu, or the inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Ieſu, conteining xv. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal petitions, which x. times re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peted, make alſo thryes Fyfty. In the whiche Pſalter and inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, is the glorious name of our Sauiour Ieſu called vpon iiij. C. and Fyfty times. whoſoeuer vſeth to ſay it, truſt they verily, that they ſhal finde therby ſpecial helpe to reſiſt tentation, and haue encreaſe of grace &amp; vertue by the ſinguler helpe of Ieſu. Of this bleſſed name S. Peter in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Actes of the Apoſtles ſayth: There is none other name vnder heauen giuen to men, in the which it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth vs to be ſaued.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:3"/>
            <p>And our Sauiour ſaith in the Goſpel of Saint Ihon, that we ſhoulde make our petitions in his name, whiche is the Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour of our ſaluation, whoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious viſion and moſt amorous fruition in the celeſtial glorie ſhal be our perpetual ioye and incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſible conſolation.</p>
            <p>Here is to be noted (as it is ſaid before) that the xv. principal peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions muſt be ſaied eche one by themſelfe, ten times, like as they ſhal be ſette forth in this booke by ordre. And ye may ſaie them vpon your ten fingers, or vpon ten beades, or els reade them as
<pb facs="tcp:7800:4"/>they be writen, and it is good for them that can not reade, to learne theſe inuocations without boke.</p>
            <p>Begynne your Pſalter with deuoute genuflexion, or at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe with inclinalion to Ieſu: &amp; ſay thus, as foloweth.</p>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="prayer">
               <head>Philipp. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>In nomine Ieſu omne genu fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatur, coeleſtium, terreſtriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernorum. Et omnis lingua confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teatur, quia Dominus Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus in gloria eſt Dei Patris.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="petition">
               <head>The fyrſt petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. mercy.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. mercy.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. mercy.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:4"/>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu Ieſu. mercy.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. mercy.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. mercy.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. merty.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. mercy.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. mercy.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. mercy.</item>
               </list>
               <p>JEſu haue mercy on me, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue me y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great offences which I haue done in the ſyght of thee.</p>
               <p>Graunt me grace, Ieſu, for the loue of thee, to deſpiſe ſynne and al wordly vanitie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on all ſynners, Ieſu, I beſeche thee: turne theyr vices into vertues, &amp; make them
<pb facs="tcp:7800:5"/>true obſeruers of thy law and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee, bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, oue very God, haue mercie on me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="petition">
               <head>The ſecond petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:5"/>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. helpe me.</item>
               </list>
               <p>IEſu helpe me, to ouercome all tentations to ſynne, &amp; the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice of my ghoſtly enemie.</p>
               <p>To ſpend my tyme in vertue &amp; labour acceptable to thee, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the motions of my fleſh in ſtouth, glotony, and leacherie.</p>
               <p>To haue myne heart enamored of vertue and the glorious pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of thee, good name &amp; fame, Ieſu, to thyne honour, and to the comforte of me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:6"/>
               <p>Haue mercy on all ſynners, Ieſu, I beſeche thee: turne theyr vices into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee, bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God haue mercie on me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="petition">
               <head>The thyrde petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:6"/>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth me.</item>
               </list>
               <p>IEſu ſtrength me in ſoule and body, to execute the workes of vertue, to the pleaſure of thee, whereby I maye come to thy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſting ioye and felicitie.</p>
               <p>Graunt me firme purpoſe, moſt mercyful Ieſu, to amend my lyfe, &amp; to recompenſe for thoſe yeres, which I haue myſpent to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure
<pb facs="tcp:7800:7"/>of thee in euil thoughtes, delectations, conſentinges, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, workes and euil cuſtomes. Alſo in breaking thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes, wherby I haue deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued damnation, &amp; thyne enmitie.</p>
               <p>Make myne heart obedient to fulfil thy will, and ready to do for thy loue the workes of pitie.</p>
               <p>Graunt me the ſeue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>n giftes of the Holy Ghoſt, the eyght beati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes, the foure cardinal vertues and in receiuing of the Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes deuoutly to diſpoſe me.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on al ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, I beſeche thee: turne their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes into vertues, and make them
<pb facs="tcp:7800:7"/>true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God, haue mercie on me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="petition">
               <head>The fourth petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:8"/>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte me.</item>
               </list>
               <p>JEſu comforte me, and gyue me grace, to haue my moſt ioy and pleaſure in thee.</p>
               <p>Sende me heauenly medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, gooſtly ſweetnes and fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour of thy glorie.</p>
               <p>Rauyſh my ſoule with bren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng deſyre to the heauenly ioye, where I ſhall euerlaſtyngly dwel with thee.</p>
               <p>Graunt me, ſweete Sauiour Ieſu, tontempte of al damnable pleaſure full of ſynne and miſerie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:8"/>
               <p>Graunt me reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of my ſaluation, with feare of da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation.</p>
               <p>Alſo reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, thy gyftes and great kynde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes ſhewed to me.</p>
               <p>Reduce into my minde my ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and vnkindenes, whereby I haue offended thee.</p>
               <p>Eraunt me the ſpirit of perfite penance, contrition, confeſſion, &amp; ſatiſfaction, to obteine thy grace: &amp; fro filthy ſinne to pourge me.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on al ſinners, Ieſu, I beſeche thee, turne theyr vices into vertues, &amp; make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> true ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruers of thy law and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting glorie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:9"/>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee: and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God, haue mercy on me. <hi>Pater. Aue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="petition">
               <head>The fyfth Petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:9"/>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu Ieſu. Make me conſtant and ſtable.</item>
               </list>
               <p>JEſu make me conſtant &amp; ſtable in faith, hope, and charitie, with continuance in vertue, and will not to offende thee.</p>
               <p>Make me oft to remembre thy Paſſion and bitter paines, which thou ſuffredſt for me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:10"/>
               <p>Sende me perfite patience in al tribulation and aduerſitie.</p>
               <p>Preſerue me fro Pryde, Ire, Enuie, Coueryſe, and from all offences to thy lawes contrary.</p>
               <p>The Catholike obſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Churche make me to kepe truely.</p>
               <p>Make my ſoule to holy doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trine obedient, &amp; to thinges per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teining to my ghoſtly weale for the loue of thee.</p>
               <p>Suffre no falſe delight of this deceiueable lyfe, by fleſhly tenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and fraude of the fende, for to blynde me.</p>
               <p>To the houre of my death, my fiue wittes, Ieſu, kepe I beſeche thee.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:10"/>
               <p>From exceſſe in ſpeaking, in feeding, and working, preſerue my frailtie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on al ſynners, Ieſu, I beſeche thee, turne theyr vices into vertues, &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy lawe, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God, haue mercy on me.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="prayer">
               <head>Philippenſ. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Dominus noſter Ieſus Chriſtus
<pb facs="tcp:7800:11"/>humiliauit femetipſum pro nobis, factus obediens vſque ad mortem, mortem autem Crucis.</p>
               <p>Pater noſter. Aue Maria. Credo.</p>
               <p>In nomine Ieſu omne genu fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatur, coeleſtium, terreſtriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernorum. Etomnis lmgua confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teatur, quia Dominus Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus in gloria eſt Dei Patris.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="petition">
               <head>The ſixt petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:11"/>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Lyght me.</item>
               </list>
               <p>IEſu light me with ghoſtly wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to knowe thy goodnes, &amp; thoſe thinges, whiche are moſt acceptable to thee.</p>
               <p>Graunt me grace to gyue good enſample to ſoules profitable, that none be hurte by me: and to helpe thoſe with good counſel, whiche haue offended thee.</p>
               <p>Make me to procede fro vertue to vertue, vnto ſuche tyme, that I ſhal clerely ſee thy Maieſtie.</p>
               <p>Lette me not turne to thoſe ſinnes, which I haue ſorowed for &amp; by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion haue accuſed me of.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:12"/>
               <p>The horrible ſentence of end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe death, the terrible Iugement of damnation, thy wrath, ire, and indignation, merciful Lord, let neuer fall vpon me.</p>
               <p>Thy mercy and thy merites, my Sauiour, euer be betwene them and me.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on al ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſn, I beſeche thee: turne their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name Ieſu.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:12"/>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God, haue mercie on me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="petition">
               <head>The ſeuenth petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace to dreade thee.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to dreade thee.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace to dreade thee.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to dreade thee.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to dreade thee.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to dreade thee.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:13"/>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to dreade thee.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to dreade thee.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to dreade thee.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to dreade thee.</item>
               </list>
               <p>IEſu graunt me grace inwardly to dreade thee, &amp; to eſchue thoſe thyngs, whereby I myght offend thee.</p>
               <p>Thy bleſſed Mother be media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trice for me, and purchace me a contrite hearte, for that I haue offended thee.</p>
               <p>Remoue my ſinfull diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,
<pb facs="tcp:7800:13"/>which dul myne hearte, and like lead do ſuppreſſe me.</p>
               <p>All thy Saintes pray for me, that I be not ſeparate fro thee and theyr bleſſed felow ſhip in the heauenly Citie.</p>
               <p>Let me not forget, good Lord, the rycheſſe of thy goodnes, of thy patience, of thy long ſufferaunce and benignitie.</p>
               <p>Let the threatning of paine &amp; tourme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, which ſhal fal vpon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, the loſſe of thy loue and of thy heauenly enherytaunce, euer feare me to offende thee.</p>
               <p>Suffre me not to lye in ſynne, but call me ſoone to penaunce,
<pb facs="tcp:7800:14"/>when I haue diſpleaſed thee: haue mercy on me.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on all ſinners Ieſu, I beſeche thee, turne theyr vices into vertues, &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God, haue mercie on me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="petition">
               <head>The eyght petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:14"/>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to loue thee.</item>
               </list>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:15"/>
               <p>JEſu graunt me grace, truely to loue thee for thy endleſſe good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, and for thoſe gyfres, which I haue receiued, and truſt to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceyue of thee.</p>
               <p>Lord, whan I offende, ſmyte me not wyth ſodeyn death, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeche the.</p>
               <p>Let the remembrannce of thy kyndenes and patience, conquere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> malice &amp; wretched deſyre in me.</p>
               <p>Drawe me, Lorde, to thee, by perfite loue and charitie.</p>
               <p>By breaking of thy commaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dementes I haue deſpiſed thee.</p>
               <p>Graunt me, good Lorde, in ke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pyng of them, as greatly to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour thee.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:15"/>
               <p>Fro leſſe ſinne that I fal not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the greater, Lord, preſerue me.</p>
               <p>Do with me according to thy mercy, and not after my miſerie: withdrawe thy ſwerde of ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geance for thy great mercy and pitie.</p>
               <p>Graunt me, Lorde, to be the childe of ſaluation, in body and ſoule to haue glorification, cleare ſight and fruition of thy Diuini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and euer preſently to ſee the glorious Trinitie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on all ſynners, Ieſu, I beſeche thee: turne theyr vices into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law,
<pb facs="tcp:7800:16"/>and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee: and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God, haue mercy on me. <hi>Pater. Aue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="petition">
               <head>The ninth Petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber. my death.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt &amp;c.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:16"/>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber my death.</item>
               </list>
               <p>IEſu, graunt me grace, for to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membre perfitly the danger of death, &amp; the great account, whiche I muſt then giue to thee, &amp; ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe me, that my ſoule be accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to thee, &amp; to thy glorious Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the bleſſed Virgin Marie.</p>
               <p>Then with the aſſiſtance of thy glorious Angel S. Mighel, deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer me fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger of my ghoſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly enemy. And thee, my good An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel, I beſeche, than to helpe me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:17"/>
               <p>Then, good Lorde, remembre thy mercy, and for myne offences turne not thy louely face fro me.</p>
               <p>O my Lord, be mercyful King, and meke Iudge at that dreadful houre, of me. I may not heare the rigour of thy righteouſnes: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I appeale to thy mercie. Thy mercie exalteth thy Iudgement, and to vs ſinners it is ſaluation, when we crie hartily to thee.</p>
               <p>At that dreadful houre helpe vs moſt mercyfull Lorde, whiche for the time now call for mercie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on al ſynners, Ieſu, I beſeche thee, turne theyr vices into vertues, &amp; make them
<pb facs="tcp:7800:17"/>true obſeruers of thy lawe, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God, haue mercy on me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="petition">
               <head>The tenth petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende me here my purgatory.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende &amp;c.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:18"/>
                  <item n="vi">vi. Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij. Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij. Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix. Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="x">x. Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Sende me here my Purgatory.</item>
               </list>
               <p>JEſu ſende me here my Purga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie, and preſerue me fro thoſe tourmentes of fyre, whiche euer ſhal puniſh ſinne and iniquitie.</p>
               <p>Let ful hope of thine helpe euer abide in me, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I neuer fal in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperation of thy endleſſe mercie. Mother of God, Patriarkes, Pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phetes, Apoſtles, Euangeliſtes, Martyrs, Confeſſours, Virgins, wydowes, Matrones &amp; Innoce<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,
<pb facs="tcp:7800:18"/>I offre me to your merites, and beſeche you, to pray for me, &amp; at my paſſing helpe to protect me.</p>
               <p>With thy Sacramentes, Lord, than recomfort me, &amp; bring me to the kingdome of endleſſe felicitie.</p>
               <p>My Lord Ieſu crucified for me, by the merites of thy glorious Paſſion, I beſeche thee, graunt me theſe petitions, which I haue axed of thee.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on al ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, I beſeche thee: turne their vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes into vettues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:19"/>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God, haue mercie on me.</p>
            </div>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="prayer">
               <head>Philipp. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>Dominus noſter Ieſus Chriſtus humiliauit ſemetipſum pronobis, fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctus obediens vſque ad morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tem autem Crucis.</p>
               <p>Pater noſter. Aue Maria. Credo.</p>
               <p>In nomine Ieſu omne genu fle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctatur, coeleſtium, terreſtriu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fernorum. Etomnis lingua confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teatur, quia Dominus Ieſus Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus in gloria eſt Dei Patris.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:19"/>
               <head>The eleuenth Petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace to flee euil companie.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to flee euil companie.</item>
               </list>
               <p>JEſu graunt me grace, to flee euil companie. And when I come among them, for thy glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I beſeche thee, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue
<pb facs="tcp:7800:20"/>me, that none occaſion of mortall ſynne ouercome me. And ſende me ghoſtly comfort, by the true louers of thee.</p>
               <p>Kepe my mouth, good Lord, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſlaunderous ſpeaking, lying, falſe witneſſe-bearing, curſing, ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, vncharitable chiding, diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute laughing &amp; wordes of vanity.</p>
               <p>Make me, bleſſed Lorde, with dreade to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bre, that thou pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently heareſt me, whiche of al my wordes ſhalt iudge me.</p>
               <p>Suffre not my heart to be light of creditte in hearing detraction, and obliquie, rancour and ire.</p>
               <p>Ieſu, repreſſe in me al inordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of carnalitie, &amp; wher
<pb facs="tcp:7800:20"/>I haue by euil felow ſhip offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, mekely I axe mercie of thee, and I beſeche thee for helpe to all that crie for mercie.</p>
               <p>Thy powrr protecte me, thy wyſdome directe me, thy ſatherly pitie correct me.</p>
               <p>Sende me gracious lyfe, bleſſed endyng, and thy Paſſion preſerue me fro euerlaſting damnation &amp; terrour of myne enemie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on all ſynners, Ieſu, I beſeche thee: turne theyr vices into vertues, and make them true obſeruers of thy law, and louers of thee, bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:21"/>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatory for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Triuitie, one very God, haue mercie on me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="petition">
               <head>The tvvelfth petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue me grace to cal for helpe to thee.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue &amp;c.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:21"/>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue me grace to cal for helpe to thee.</item>
               </list>
               <p>IEſu graunt me grace, &amp; ſpecially in the time of te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tation, to cal for helpe to thee, &amp; then with faithful mind to remembre thy Paſſion, which thou ſuffredſt for me: than, moſt merciful Lord, kepe my ſoule <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o conſent of ſinne for very true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oue of thee: tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> let ſinne appeare <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>inking and abhominable to me.</p>
               <p>Let the remembraunce of the paines of hel, &amp; damnation horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and terrible, &amp; ful of thine en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, with the merites of thy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>cke patience, through charitie &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:7800:22"/>chaſtitie, mitigate the pronitie to ſinne and frailtie in me.</p>
               <p>In my tentations, Lorde, I beſeche thee, helpe me, for the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der loue, that thou didſt ſhew to thy Mother, and ſhe to thee.</p>
               <p>Repel the power of my aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, whiche entende the dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of me.</p>
               <p>Inhabite my ſoule, o Sauiour, which with al hunible ſubiection deſireth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> bleſſed preſence of thee.</p>
               <p>Make me pure in ſpirite, meke in ſpeaking, parrient in ſuffring, hungrie of righteouſe working, and merciful to all them that be in miſerie.</p>
               <p>Make me peaſable in conuer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſation,
<pb facs="tcp:7800:22"/>cleane in heart with holy meditation, and ioyfully to ſuffre perſecution in the cauſe of thee.</p>
               <p>Let all my powers and deſires be ruled according to the will of thee: and al my petitions order to thy wyſdome, and to the euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting profite of me.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on all ſynners, Ieſu, I beſeche thee: turne theyr vices into vertues, &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy lawe, and louers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.
<pb facs="tcp:7800:23"/>The holy Trinitie, one very God, haue mercy on me. <hi>Pater. Aue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="petition">
               <head>The thyrienth petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer in v<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:aber"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>er</ex>
                     </expan>tue acceptable to thee.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Make me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer in v<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:aber"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>er</ex>
                     </expan>tue acceptable to thee.</item>
               </list>
               <p>IEſu, make me perſeuerant in the bleſſed ſeruice of thee.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:23"/>
               <p>In holy cuſtome and vertuous occupation, Lord, kepe my ſoule and my body.</p>
               <p>Make me flee ſinfull delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and patiently to ſuffer iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries and rebukes, in recompenſe of my diſobedient heart to thee.</p>
               <p>Prouide, good Lorde, that life to me, whiche thou knoweſt moſt to thine honour, and to my eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal felicitie.</p>
               <p>Fyll myne heart with contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and myne eyes with teares, that I neuer be forſaken of thee.</p>
               <p>Awake my dull ſoule fro ſiepe of ſinne: and ſend me helpe fro heauen, my bleſſed Sauiour, to
<pb facs="tcp:7800:24"/>ouercome the olde ſerpent with al his cautels, by exercyſe in vertue, and ſpecial grace of thee.</p>
               <p>The Angels of light deliuer me fro the Angels of darkenes, and fro theyr great crueltie.</p>
               <p>Let thy obedience, Lorde, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compenſe for mine obſtinacie, thy abſtinence, for my ſuperfiuitie, thy mekenes and thy patience for my pride, ireful heart and enmitie.</p>
               <p>Thy charitie for my malice, thy deuotio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for my dulnes, thy louing heart for mine vnkindenes, thy holy death for my wretched lyfe, and for al my miſerie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on al ſynners, Ieſu, I beſeche thee, turne theyr
<pb facs="tcp:7800:24"/>vices into vertues, &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in Purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Triuitie, one very God, haue mercy on me. <hi>Pater. Aue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="petition">
               <head>The fourtenth petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i. Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vi">vi Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt, &amp;c.</item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:7800:25"/>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Graunt me grace, to fixe my mind on thee.</item>
               </list>
               <p>IEſu, graunt me grace, ſpecially in the time of praier, to fixe my minde on thee, and then remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bre my wretchednes, &amp; faithfully to cal for helpe to thee.</p>
               <p>That time to remembre the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilles of body and ſoule, which I haue eſcaped, &amp; the benefites that I haue receiued thorough thy great charitie: &amp; with al my heart Lorde then to giue laude to thee.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:25"/>
               <p>In this praier I thanke thee, for al the creatures, whiche thou haſt made to helpe man, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thou haſt made him to thine image fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally in thy glorie to honor thee.</p>
               <p>The motions of my running minde, the deſpre of mine vnſtable hearte in time of praier, ſtop and ſtaie, I beſeche thee.</p>
               <p>Repreſſe the power of my goſtly enemies, which then draw my minde fro ghoſtly weale to many imaginations of vanitie.</p>
               <p>With the hande of thy feruent loue than I beſeche thee to take me: &amp; ſtrength me in thy power, and with thy goodnes glad me.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:26"/>
               <p>Kepe me ſo occupied in good workes, that my praiers may be acceptable to thee.</p>
               <p>Heare nowe, ſwete Sauiour Ieſu, heare the voice of a ſinner, which would faine loue thee, and with the heart as greatly pleaſe thee, as euer it hath offended thee: &amp; if it pleaſe thy grace, more large<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly to recompe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe, it beſecheth thee.</p>
               <p>Ieſu, ſaue mine enemies fro thine enmity, &amp; forgiue them that they haue offended me, like as I would be forgiue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in thoſe thinges whereby I haue offended thee.</p>
               <p>Lord, help al thoſe, which haue holpen me, or praied for me, or ſhewed to me any dede of pitie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:26"/>
               <p>Thy grace, Lorde, and the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of they pretious blood, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende me fro the ſtriking Angell and the ſpirite of peſtilence, and make him to ouerpaſſe me.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on al ſinners, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, I beſeche thee: turne theyr vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces into vertues, &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinirie, one very God haue mercie on me. <hi>Pater. Aue.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="petition">
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:27"/>
               <head>The fyftenth petition.</head>
               <list>
                  <item n="i">i Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Gyue me grace to order my life to thee.</item>
                  <item n="ij">ij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Giue me &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iij">iij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Giue me &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="iiij">iiij Ieſu. Ieſu Ieſu. Giue me &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="v">v Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Giue me &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="vij">vij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Giue me &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="viij">viij Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Giue me &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="ix">ix Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Giue me &amp;c.</item>
                  <item n="x">x Ieſu. Ieſu. Ieſu. Giue me grace to order my life to thee.</item>
               </list>
               <p>JEſu giue me grace, to order my life and the workes of my body &amp; ſoule with actual entent finally to thee, &amp; to the reward of thy in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiuitie ioy and eternal felicitie.</p>
               <pb facs="tcp:7800:27"/>
               <p>The water and blood, which ranne fro thy bleſſed heart, waſſh my ſoule from ſinne &amp; iniquitie, and purchace to me abundance of grace faithfully to ſerue thee.</p>
               <p>O my Lord, my life, my might, my ſight, leade me, feede me, and ſpede me, in the pilgrimage of this mortalitie.</p>
               <p>Graunt me, Lorde, by the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rites of thy Paſſion, and vertue of thy moſt excellent and glorious Diuinitie, what ſo euer thy wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome knoweth moſte expedient to me, whiche my miſerable life is not worthy to obteine of thee.</p>
               <p>At the houre of death (when I
<pb facs="tcp:7800:28"/>ſhal be accuſed afore thee) for that death that thou ſuffredſt for ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, haue mercy on me.</p>
               <p>Breake my froward heart, and make it obedient to thee. Fro ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dain and vnforeſene death, Lord, preſerue me.</p>
               <p>Graunt me grace, to departe with contempte of this worlde, &amp; with ioyful heart to come to thee.</p>
               <p>Let the remembrance of thy Paſſion, make me ioyfully to take tentation and tribulation for the loue of thee.</p>
               <p>Make me moſt to loue that ioyfull lyfe, that immortal glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, moſt excellent bliſſe, and end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe
<pb facs="tcp:7800:28"/>felicitie, which is ordeined in the heauenly kingdomme for the ſeruauntes of thee.</p>
               <p>By the vertue of thy Incarna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, Natiuitie, Paſſion &amp; Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, graunt me theſe ſupplica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which I haue made to thee.</p>
               <p>This inuocation &amp; Pſalter of thee, by the meditation of thy moſt intierly beloued Mother, pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chace to me gracious life &amp; bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ending, free fro dette &amp; deadly ſinne, I beſeche thee, and after my bodily death, euerlaſting life, with endleſſe bliſſe and felicitie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy on all ſynners Ieſu, I beſeche thee: turne theyr
<pb facs="tcp:7800:29"/>vices into vertues, &amp; make them true obſeruers of thy law, and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers of thee: bring them to bliſſe in euerlaſting glorie.</p>
               <p>Haue mercy alſo on the ſoules in purgatorie for thy bitter Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, I beſeche thee, and for thy glorious name, Ieſu.</p>
               <p>The holy Trinitie, one very God haue mercie on me.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Dominus noſter Ieſus Chriſtus humiliauit ſemetipſum pro nobis, fa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ctus obediens vſque ad morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, mor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tem autem Crucis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Pater noſter. Aue Maria. Credo.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Thus endeth this Pſalter.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="instructions_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:29"/>
            <head>An Admonition.</head>
            <p>VNto ſuch, as haue none op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunitie to ſaie the whole Pſalter together, it is good that they faie the firſt v. pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions one daie, and the ſecond v. another day, and the laſt v. ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther day, &amp; ſo in three dayes they ſhal ſay y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> whole Pſalter. But els if they may haue co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uenient time, it is better to ſay the xv. principal petitions euery day, &amp; ech of them x. times, with <hi>In nomine Ieſu,</hi> in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> beginning, <hi>Pater noſt. Aue Maria.</hi> &amp; at euery fifth, like as it is write<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the boke, with <hi>Dominus noſter, Pater noſter. Aue Maria. Credo.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="doctrine">
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:30"/>
            <head>Here foloweth a holſome doctrine, howe to reſiſt &amp; ouercome the ghoſtly tentations of the Fende.</head>
            <p>DOctours do write, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> in ſpiritual tentations we ſhould behaue ouerſelfe other wyſe, than in carnal tentations. For carnal tentations we ought to reſiſt &amp; wreſtle with them: but we may not do ſo in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual tentations. wyſely and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretely we muſt reſiſt them, but in no wiſe wreſtle with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as thus. when the enemie purteth a motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of infidelitie, reaſon not with him: &amp; likewyſe when he caſteth a ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtion of deſperation, ſtryue not with him, but vſe this medicine.</p>
            <p>Suſpend your reaſon, reſtraine al your ſenſes, and plucke vp al your ſpirites: &amp; as the motio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cometh, ſo let it paſſe, without ſirife. If it be only of the diſpoſition of our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
<pb facs="tcp:7800:30"/>nature, this is ſufficient, if it be vſed. If it come of the enemie, he wil not leaue ſo, but he wil cleaue otherwyſe, &amp; worke more trouble. Than after y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> counſel of Doctours, vſe this remedie: Diſſunble, &amp; ſhew yourſelf to ſet it at nought, though it be great: &amp; lift vp your mynd to God, remembring his tendre mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie in the redemption of man, and how it is his ordinance, with ſuch tentations and paines to proue his ſeruantes, to whom be entendeth to giue the crowne of glorie. But if the enemie be fierce and wil not ceaſſe for this (as he is moſt ſubtill and crafty) tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> meeke your ſolfe to God, &amp; offre yourſelfe to fuffre for his loue (&amp; for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fruit of penance for your ſinnes) gladly &amp; with thanks of heart, all paines, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it ſhall pleaſe his grace to ſende you. And with
<pb facs="tcp:7800:31"/>that, call &amp; crie with heart &amp; worde on y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy name of Ieſu x. times, or more or leſſe, as your deuotion ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, with ſome holy &amp; ſwete medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of reuerence to the ſame, as God ſhal put in your minde. This vertue of mekenes, &amp; confeſſion of the name of Ieſu in heart &amp; worde, the enemie may not abide. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though for a time he wil pretende &amp; ſemble, as though he were not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſhed for that vertue &amp; name, as the Serpent, of which Scripture ſaith, that for a time ſhe wil ſtoppe her eares, &amp; yet by the worde of the enchanter in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion ſhe is ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come &amp; taken: ſo certanily y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemie (y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy name named) is ouercome, although he wil not be knowe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but ſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>time will make inſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> more fiercely, after y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> holy name ſpoken. Then ſtrongly purſewe him with
<pb facs="tcp:7800:31"/>the ſame, &amp; with mekenes, &amp; ye ſhal ſee, how he wil flee: to the great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forte of all them, that abide as true ſeruantes perſeuera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t in this theyr proofe, to theyr great triumph, and vtter co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſion of the enemie. This hath ben proued by experience.</p>
            <div type="story">
               <head>A Narration.</head>
               <p>A certaine perſon there was, whiche by the ſpace of two yeares &amp; more was troubled with ſuche motions ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>times by water &amp; by lande. He had motions to deſpera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> moſt abhominable that may be, to deſtroy himſelfe both by water, &amp; otherwyſe. And this ſaid perſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ceaſſed not, but called to God daily, to ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth him, euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing himſelfe his ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> worſhipper of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holy name of Ieſu, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting himſelf only &amp; wholy to the Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt &amp; mercy of God. And ſone
<pb facs="tcp:7800:32"/>after the ſaid time he had comfort, &amp; was illumined or lightened in his ſoule, how to anſwere y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> enemie: to his great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> edifiyng of other, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> was thus. It was giuen to him by a light, that when ſoeuer ſuche a motion came to his minde, he ſhould take y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> motion for an oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion of reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance to honour the Paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt, &amp; his bleſſed Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the glorions Virgin Marie.</p>
               <p>And although that it came to his minde an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dred times in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> daie, ſo oft to ſay: <hi>Adoramus te, Chriſte Ieſu:</hi> &amp; to the Mother of mercy, <hi>Aue Maria.</hi> And thus y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> perſon was cleane de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuered from his great tentation &amp; trouble, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> great encreaſe of hope in his ſoule, to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> vtter drtuig away of the enemie, &amp; to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glorie of God: to whom be al honour and praiſe, world without end, Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:32"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:33"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:7800:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
